[SPEAKER_00]: I was reflecting today on what is the common thread... what is in common to all... everything that's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is... what is the common thread between everything that's unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Unwholesome acts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I've got my own thoughts on that, but... what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, tell me what you reflected.
[SPEAKER_00]: To me, it's anything, when you attempt to take away that which is, would conceal that which is with that which isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... certain contradiction then, there's a certain discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what's in common to everything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if something is unwholesome, means there is a... it contains a discrepancy in itself, which is what contradiction is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that goes against the way things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this, and I try to remove that and replace it with something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but it's it's not just like go against the way things are, but in itself is against things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that contradiction is in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not between wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying unwholesome things are unwholesome because they go against wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they are unwholesome because in themselves they have contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I think about the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can look at each precept and you can see that same thread running through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take for killing, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am taking away that which is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have no right, I have no...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not entitled to your life or to any other being's life, not even to my own life, but to take something which is not mine and take it away, take it as though it were mine and destroy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... Yeah, so it's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something that's not yours,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're basically destroying, as if it were yours, as if you're in charge, as if you're in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is mind to use, is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, another thing is... Life is implicitly valuable for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even, by the way, people who decide to...
[SPEAKER_01]: People who don't necessarily have a view that the life is worth living, still they can only do that on the basis of being alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why everybody will fear death, except Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be ready for death, even if you want to kill yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will surprise you, what death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only Arahant is truly unmoved in the face of death, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means that life in itself
[SPEAKER_01]: Being alive is taken at its face value and it has that value.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you, as the one who implicitly values life, it's taking life of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another discrepancy of the values, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you value life, you're now acting towards destroying life, intentionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: As though life were not valuable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: As though life is not valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that to me, it's not like a contradiction between wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's within yourself, within your own values, within your own principles.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually, that's why unwholesome is universally unwholesome for everyone, because for everyone it contradicts those universal values.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is valuable within you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you say my life is not valuable, you can only say that on the basis of life which you value.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're trying to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're trying to cover up and conceal that value.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not explicitly, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's implied in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not even completely think about it at all, whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean... You're not trying to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Engaging in unwholesome means that's the discrepancy you're accepting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you have to do is not think about unwholesome as... All you need to do is not understand unwh
[SPEAKER_00]: You're born up, you're born into that kind of concealment already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, yes, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like you start now... You're not like born with the fully developed concealments, but as the Buddha said, all the underlying tendencies for those concealments are there present in the newborn.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they will grow, they will develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your... that ignorance there, it's not something that you decided to do before.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you made a choice when you were five years old.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will conceal things now.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The truth of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is all mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's part of pretty much the way you attend to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's implicit in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when you attend to something, you automatically have to ignore something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot attend to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's that's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the principle of avijjā, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: By looking this way, you will not be able to look at the other way at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is the most common way that people choose to look?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the way of least resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the way of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the way of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the way of passion, desire, satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the way, basically, of the grain, with the flow.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, automatically, simply attending to that way means you're not attending to the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot attend to the both at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to find a good reason to start looking upstream and then start swimming upstream, while everything is trying to pull you down downstream.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just in the precepts again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, and by the way, I just want to say, that's why... that's why the only one who truly understands wholesome as wholesome and unwholesome as unwholesome, as in the universal value of wholesome and unwholesome, is a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't know what's truly skillful and what's truly unskillful, unless you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or that whole picture... Well, that's what the right view is, understanding the universal value of wholesome and unwholesome, and then you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will know the root of wholesome and the root of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when they asked the Buddha, so what is Sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, Sotāpanna is the one who knows skillful as skillful, or kusala as kusala, wholesome as wholesome, and he knows unwholesome as unwholesome, akusala as akusala.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you say that, then, that which is unwholesome is that which goes against the way things are?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but I don't like using the way things are, because that had been overused and quite mystified already.
[SPEAKER_00]: Goes against the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It goes against the universal principles.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the universal principles?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma is the universal law, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Goes against the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Goes against the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any... that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, be a sotāpanna, to know what those universal principles are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can't have an idea of what the natural and nature's law is, and then define, infer from there what is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can... that can only be on the level of that kind of abstract view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can correspond to the practical application to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people can kind of have an accurate... but you haven't truly understood the nature of wholesome as wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why is wholesome wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see it for yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is unwholesome unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see that for yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if we just go to the next, that precept of...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's not stealing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not taking something which is not given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, that's the whole... you're taking away something which isn't yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can also... that's why, like, you cannot accidentally break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perception is the fundamental factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you perceive something as truly yours, and you take it because you perceive it as yours, you mistaken it for something else that looks the same that was yours, there's no stealing involved there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stealing requires your intentional effort to override, which is what the discrepancy is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, intentional effort to override the value of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is implicit, even if you don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentional effort to override the value of ownership, which is implicit, but you choose to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentional effort to go and, I don't know, if it's the five precepts to seduce other people's partners, or cheat... Again, all of the discrepancies that you then intentionally choose to ignore, and double down in your action towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why these things are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have no perception, like in the sutta, as we mentioned it before, like accidentally, there was an accident and somebody died as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't an offense of killing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when there's that story in the Vinaya of the two monks who got in an argument, and then only one of them had a water filter, and he didn't want to give it to the other one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they were, like, I'm not giving his mind, he offended him or something, and then the other monk died of thirst, because he didn't want to drink it to break the rule, so he died of thirst.
[SPEAKER_01]: Passed out and couldn't recover and then died.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first monk wasn't parājika, it wasn't an offense of killing another monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it would have said, ok, well, next time you should not withhold anything out of ill will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was an offense of a completely different kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the level of, oh, he's not a monk anymore, because he killed another monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to intend.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that other monk said, I will not give you the water, with the intention of, he'll die of thirst, yeah, then, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he'd had no such intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why intention is the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot judge the action, the outcome of action, the severity of action, without ignoring the intention behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the one we mentioned in previous talk, the monk who accidentally sat on that bed, like with pillars, and there was a baby underneath and killed it, broke its neck or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everybody said, okay, well, next time if you sit down without checking where you're sitting, it's an offense of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although that wrongdoing resulted in death of a baby, but it wasn't intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So intention is that factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you choose to act with intention of ill-will,
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire, carelessness, means you're accepting that contradiction, that value, the contradicting value.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're choosing to go down that way, because it's too unpleasant to resist it, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's step back.
[SPEAKER_00]: That precept of refraining from sexual misconduct or having sexual relations with
[SPEAKER_00]: People you shouldn't, you know, another's wife or...
[SPEAKER_01]: Protected, underage, all these things, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just taking again, misappropriating things which are... Yeah, so you perceive it, you perceive it generally as not yours, as shouldn't be engaged with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you choose to give priority to your desire and ignore the factual basis of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give priority to your desires, not the others.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mine is first, mine is more important, mine is more valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even passion, even if it's passion within the precepts, even if it's sort of annoyance and ill will, but you don't break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where this contradiction is already rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when it comes to precepts, it's just a further manifestation of you acting out of that contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But passion in itself, desire in itself, ill-will in itself, delusion or dullness in itself, that's in itself, that's already that contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why these things are unwholesome and these things always result in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you take the precepts...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is passion contradiction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is a desire a contradiction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Individually, from your own point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire towards anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that desire an existential contradiction or contradiction on an existential level?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the discrepancy there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you want something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you cannot have.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I mean, you can have things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean you can't have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just took it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's not necessarily a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a more fundamental level, why is it contradictory to have a desire, even if you don't go and take it, even if you don't break the precepts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it contradictory to have a desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: To cultivate a desire, to welcome a desire, to delight in a desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, desire is always
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot have a desire that's not towards sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always has... it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever you desire, it's going to be one of these six things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have any of these six things without the senses being there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the mind being there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have sights without the eye?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds without ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the nature of the eye, ear, nose, body, tongue, mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the nature of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then cultivate a desire towards that which you can only get on account of things that are not yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way you can cultivate desire towards those things is to take these things to be yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's impossible for you to have a desire towards sense objects without implicitly taking the ownership of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought I was saying that, actually, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't... you might have been saying it in general terms, but I didn't kind of see that you were saying it on the level of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't act, even if you don't break the precepts, even if you don't do anything, having a desire that is being welcomed and delighted in and accepted and not understood, is already that existential contradiction we talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will not be able to welcome a desire, entertain it, even if you don't act out of it, without that entertainment of that desire implicitly taking up the sense bases as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking up Mara's domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was going to say just now.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more such the precept of not acting out of sensuality, you know, being celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're no longer taking these senses to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not acting out of sensuality, being celibate, is the necessary sort of precondition for you to then eventually not take these senses to be yours on the level of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: A monk can live withdrawn from centrality, but if he hasn't understood it, uprooted it internally, on the level of his thoughts, he's still bound by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then gave the simile, like, you can step outside of the water, and get the sticks to light the fire, but because they're still wet because of that water, you won't light the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you need to wait for them to dry up, and not keep going back to the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to live withdrawn from centrality physically, as a celibate, but then also mentally you need to start withdrawing your mind so it dries up from that centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can stop taking that which is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because taking up what's not yours starts on the level of welcoming a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: By welcoming it, you take it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you take up desire, you take every value that that desire implies.
[SPEAKER_01]: The value is that senses are in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Senses can be enjoyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dangerous to enjoy the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not dangerous to pursue whatever they take you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're acting from a premise that these senses are mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense experience is safe, secure.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that's implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lovely.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is completely implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even, you don't even think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that whole delighting and so on is already... That's because he doesn't delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't say desire to not manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no say in that, but you have a say in your attitude towards the manifestation of desire, or your will, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I welcoming?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I relishing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I kind of rejoicing in the prospect of desire and then fulfilling that desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if then I practice sense restraint, am I still entertaining a phenomenon of desire in my experience when desire manifests?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you do, that's why you're still contradicting yourself on the existential basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you cannot possibly entertain, as I said, the value of desire, without implicitly taking up the ownership of the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop valuing the sense objects, stop entertaining desire towards them, you get to uproot taking up the sense bases as yours, the sense organs as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have desire,
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards sense objects, because you've misappropriated the sense senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's like a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because you appropriate the senses, as in, you don't question your ownership of them, of your eye, nose, ear, the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you cultivate desire towards the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you cultivate desire towards sense objects, that's how you appropriate the sense organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one feeds the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first you need to stop... first you need to start restraining your behavior on account of the desire towards sense objects, as in you need to start keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, once you're established in that, once that becomes your norm of behavior,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can get to see that on the mental level, you should now stop delighting in it, welcoming it, sort of flirting it in your mind and accepting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you know you're not gonna act physically, now you make the further effort and don't welcome it with the mind, don't engage in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, through not... basically, you will dry out of that wetness, of that desire, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you get to see the true nature of those senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh my goodness, this is peril.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is like... Each time I was engaging with the desire towards sense objects, it was like putting my head on a chopping block, which is what the sense organ is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the axe could have fallen at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Balancing on this...
[SPEAKER_01]: This insecure thing... Well, yeah, you basically, because of your desire to sense organs, you go into a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, because of your desire to sense objects, you go into the trap of sense organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... we've done that... the simile... the lion's reserve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lion's enclosure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are making yourself... like, you're exposing yourself to this danger, to this peril, to this risk, to death, deadly suffering, because of your desires towards sense objects, which implies the ownership of sense organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sense organs are that chopping block, are that... are that... are that trap, and lion's den, and so on, that you walk into.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't just say, okay, I'm not regarding my senses as mine anymore, because that thought of your senses, it's basically a sense object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot directly experience your sense organs, which is why there's always that implicit ownership that you need to undo indirectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just decide, I'll let go of this, because you're not holding it intentionally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is... what else do you need to let go?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, what is the only other thing that you... if you let go, then you will not have the ownership of the sense organs?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, it's the desire to sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let go of that, you step closer to then let go of the sense organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think you're letting go of sense organs, you're regarding your own sense organs as sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not being overly into perceptions,
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're not delighting it, you're not focusing and you're not entangled within your perceptions, you can let go of them, so to speak, to step back to see what's behind there, what they are based upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but like, when you see, when you want to see what's behind, it's not like another thing you want to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, you mustn't act out of it, out of that delight and desire, and then you need to understand it, understand that desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing else you need to sort of psychologize out of it, to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to understand the nature of that thing, which is right there, that desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: The peril, the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep saying it's implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not found in response to this desire or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is in every desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: In every time you delight in any desire of any kind, all these things are implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these universal values are implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the eye cannot see itself, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sense organs cannot see itself as a sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: or of its corresponding nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Utterly impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you think you're letting go of your eyes, of your body, you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're basically... that thought is misconceiving sense objects to be the sense organ.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, you can imagine an eye, but that's not the eye because of which you have sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to abandon the I, because of which... to abandon the ownership of I, because of which you have sights, is to see the peril of the desire towards sights, the danger to not delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you've sufficiently seen that, the mind will withdraw itself from the domain of sights, and by doing so, implicitly, withdraw that ownership of the domain of sights as I, the sense object of the sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are lured by something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Driven by something else, and you walk into a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never see the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you wouldn't trap you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you withdraw yourself from the particular bait that traps you, and that's how you escape the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't see the trap, but you can see the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the bait?
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire in regard to sights is the Mara's bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remove the desire towards sights,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no entering the trap of any kind, so you don't need to worry about the, like, specificity of a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hmm, this is how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I think this, they say, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: No desire towards sights, no trap of any kind that you can walk into.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to think what's the next precept of the... Third... Did we do the third?
[SPEAKER_01]: We did, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the lying, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I said lying already.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, I don't... No, it was feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what I thought it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, lying is misrepresenting the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentionally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, fundamentally, you are... you are living concealment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the biggest lie, which you kind of... Yeah, the biggest lie is that the fundamental lie of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to use the word ignorance necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of avijjā, the fundamental lie of delusion, dullness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, would you be able, for example,
[SPEAKER_01]: To be complacent, lazy, dull and careless, if you're placed in a dangerous situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you perceive the danger of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be inconceivable for you to relax on that level, to like completely just let your mind kind of melt away and forget about itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, here you are, in the most perilous situation you can be,
[SPEAKER_01]: With death, sickness, aging, everything else is approaching elements from all the directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't escape it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, here you are, completely complacent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the fundamental contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hardest one to undo.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not as obvious as desire or as it will.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is danger, but you just don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like the danger doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just for example, if you if you want to do a little experiment, if you're not sure if it's dangerous or not, your existence in itself,
[SPEAKER_01]: Just lock yourself in a room, comfortable room, but don't engage with any distraction for a day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Switch your phone off, switch everything, don't talk to anyone, don't step outside, just sit alone on a chair or a bed, whatever else, and stare in the wall.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... let's see how long you can do that before you start freaking out on account of that boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if boredom is not truly dangerous, why are you so afraid of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you constantly need something to keep you engaged, to swim, so you don't sink deep down?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you terrified of solitude and loneliness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, like, 99.99% people are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you need to make the effort to basically develop your mind and wisdom in order to be able to delight in solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you realize that, oh, if I'm... Say if I get sick and I can't move.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can't distract myself with all these things and projects I have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: How will my mind remain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Will it be unaffected by this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or will I start completely losing it and freaking out?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so, I'm bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, let the boredom endure now, and it's going to turn into full-blown anxiety and dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why is that, if existence is not dangerous and perilous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does this anxiety come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't done anything, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in a perfectly safe environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Locked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody can get in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Safe as you can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, here you are freaking out internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because that's what existence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all these efforts and actions you do,
[SPEAKER_01]: To enable yourself to ignore that very nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why delusion, like lobha, dosa, moha, the three kind of unwholesome outpours, that's why they're unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delusion being the third one, or dullness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That dullness is a form of complacency.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only way you... like, you cannot be complacent without implicit kind of... without implicitly sort of assuming or ignoring the fact
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: That existence is not perilous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just assume safety, because you are complacent, and because you assume safety, you make the effort toward complacency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same like with that, what we said, with the desire and ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the best thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: One has to understand that anicca is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, anicca is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by seeing that dukkha, because of... By seeing anicca, and by seeing anicca is dukkha, you're then implicitly withdrawing yourself from the ownership of atta, which is anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that seeing dukkha means that you are no longer, yeah, complacent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be complacent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you need to see that dukkha, and the dukkha of boredom is the dukkha of this is, the dukkha of uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's so many ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing that dukkha is like seeing your executioner with his sword drawn out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Waiting for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's waiting for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have that... you can't go... you can't relax and just watch a movie now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like somebody comes and tells you, I have 10 minutes to live.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just carry on watching this movie and laughing carelessly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be impossible for you to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suddenly, the sense of urgency is back on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason sense of urgency can be kind of restored is because it's always there implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: That anxiety, that thread of anxiety, that you can never completely cover up, is what human existence is, for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: People who practice, people who don't practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody can outrun it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only Arhat can free himself from it completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, by trapping yourself into a room or whatever... Yeah, so... but when you are, like, young, healthy, you have all the senses working, everything at your disposal, it feels like there's no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, just do a little experiment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Close yourself in for like half a day and see what's gonna start happening to your own mind when there are no distractions available.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if your mind was problem-free beforehand, this would not cause any issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Solitude starts basically... Because you're revealing what's actually there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're taking away... Well, you're revealing what's your main motivator for all this engagement with life, is to cover up the fact that it's perilous and underlying anxiety that sort of means you're not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that, as you said before, the whole practice
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about unconcealing things, or in a suit, as it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Undoing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Removing this and concealing that which is covered.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncovering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's a way to say, like a skilled butcher gets the first, you know, the skin off, the meat, the tendons, sinews, everything uncovering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like analyzing on an abstract level, which is sometimes how people take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means uncovering all the layers of a cover-up until you get to the core.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... fifth precept on... Intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you possibly engage with intoxicating substances without implicitly endorsing complacency and dullness of your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just have fun.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's just like, you know, I don't necessarily get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Engaging with that substance, to some extent,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is increasing dullness of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of heedlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless there is no alcohol in the substance, which always results in increasing... Well, dullness means heedlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dullness means loss of context, loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's for a grain a bit, like not as much as you're completely drunk, it's still the direction of losing context and perspective, even if it's half a step.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still that same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as the Buddha said, same.
[SPEAKER_01]: A pound of excrement is equally disgusting as a little grain of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Smells horrible, looks horrible, and tastes horrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact that you engage a little bit, maybe, oh, I only take a glass of wine, I don't get drunk, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I only take a scoop of excrement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the result of dullness, even if it's miniscule.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mental dullness is still the result of your action, which means you still value it, you're still engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you engage with even like a sort of absolute minimal level, so to speak, of intoxication, just tiny bit, without valuing, without delighting at the prospect of dullness of the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Preferring that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Numbness, dullness, distraction, any of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which means, can you... can you be engaging with that direction of intoxicating your mind even a tiny bit, without sort of not seeing the danger of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to engage with it if you see it as dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I will not go all the way into the lion's den.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just set the foot inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but what if the lion is right there by the entrance?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is a chance that it might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you wouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't flirt with that idea at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: A little bit of poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: A little bit of poison is still a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lot of poison, but it's still a poison, which means it still affects you, which means that might be enough in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're already covered, like you're already full of wrong views in regard to everything, in regard to desire, in regard to ill-will, in regard to dullness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's already like a mountain of work for all of that to be undone, as we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, here you are flirting with the things that directly result in increasing of those wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, literally, a glass of wine might be enough for you to fully cement you in your wrong views that sensuality is not bad or not see it as dangerous enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, you will not get the right view and you will remain bound to saṃsāra for eons to come.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the glass of wine really worth that risk?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you really know that that risk is not implied?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the slightest clue.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just wishful thinking and believe in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, you perceive that it's not as bad as two liters of wine, but it doesn't mean that it's not bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's based on the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a whole... it had taken intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what they were... sorry, there was that case of a man with the right view in the sutta, who was drinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who wasn't practicing, he got a right view, then stopped practicing, because he was happy with the right view, and then got careless in his precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when he was basically dying, he undertook the training again, and pretty much stopped drinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's like for a day, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had the basis of right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Buddha said, well, for him, it was different, because why?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if he was absolutely pissing drunk, every single day of his life,
[SPEAKER_01]: Having developed the right view beforehand, he cannot develop the wrong views now.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's certainly not pursuing the direction of the right view that results in arahantship, but he cannot undo the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the amount of drinking, the amount of engaging in breaking the precepts, cannot proliferate his wrong views, which is exactly what happens to somebody without the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's also exactly why it's very unlikely that somebody with the right view would break those precepts like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, there is always exception to every rule, and that's why two and a half thousand years later, we're still talking about that man.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he made it into the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: He stood out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of them would not do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for whatever reasons, he had his reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: One in a million has done that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, you use that one example, pretty much anecdotal evidence, to say that you, without the right view, is fine to drink, because sotāpanna can drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so drinking, you can match that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't you match the right view of a sotāpanna as well, and then see how you can drink?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or how you can break the precepts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, theoretically you could, but not until you get the right view first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm just explaining, like, how it did not affect him.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it affected him, obviously, because he could have become an arahant in this life, but it did not affect him in the same sense as somebody without a right view, even just not seeing the danger in the tiny little step towards intoxication and dullness, might be more than enough for fully solidifying wrong views that you should have been undoing, which means you will not... you will not get the right view as a result of you lacking development on the... in the domain of precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even, like, we proposed to that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: The suttas were never... even when the Buddha was teaching lay people, before they would get the right view, he would start teaching them the, like, you know, benefits of virtue, generosity, and then the peril of sensuality, how it's of little value, little satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the mind would be primed like that, then he would teach them, and then they would get to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they might go back to their wives and husbands and so on, but they can't undo what they understood, which means they'll never be able to be as careless.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, if you get the right view and then choose to go back to centrality, that's your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But saying, because the one with the right view can go to centrality, means I can do centrality without a right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's just ignorant thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentionally ignorant thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you obviously see that it's not the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's similar to intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intoxication with life, intoxication with health, intoxication with...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, of course, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean, losing the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: That still context is that, oh, yeah, I might be healthy and alive and young now, but can I guarantee that there will be the next in and out breath?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be a lot... No, you have absolutely no guarantee of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you don't think about that, that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you fall away from recognizing that context, then you start heading into the direction of the desire towards sense objects, which is intoxication as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the more subtle application of that precept.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go deeper there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking no intoxicants, no longer intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but I don't get drunk when I drink one glass of wine or one beer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're intoxicated with life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being drunk is not a measure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of whether you're wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Engaging with the unwholesome direction is a measure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter if you engage ten steps into the unwholesome direction on one step, you're accepting the direction of unwholesome full stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's this again, like, common sort of pututjana's wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody says you shouldn't get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You shouldn't drink alcohol, but not drinking alcohol, you cannot get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is this...
[SPEAKER_01]: Drunk is being the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Drinking alcohol is the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you get drunk, but because it's implicitly taking up of the unwholesome direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even a tiny bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you won't have to be worried about whether you're drunk or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was never the threshold for the precept.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was never the threshold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the precept doesn't say don't get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says don't consume intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_01]: They then result in drunkenness and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I don't get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have you consumed intoxicants?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to consume intoxicants without implicit value of mental dullness and relaxation, basically, on the level of ignoring the necessary context of perilous existence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, you're gonna die in five minutes, but let's have a glass of wine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's get drunk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Help you deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there anything I can do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I might have a chance to save myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you have a chance to save yourself, but forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's enjoy ourselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one would you choose, even as the one who values alcohol and party and everything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: You would choose to do something about it when you recognize that you could.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason now you will be accepting the direction of distraction, intoxication, relaxation on the level of mental dullness, would be because you're completely unaware of the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will not become aware of the danger on account of choosing the direction of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the other precepts of
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no entertainment, no decoration.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're now going to eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, in general, you can find the same in any precept.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, same, same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you engage with entertainment, beautification and adornment without implying the ownership of that which you are entertaining, adoring and beautifying?
[SPEAKER_01]: without implying the value of this thing is beautiful and worth embellishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, would you be embellishing a poisonous drink that just smelling it might kill you, let alone touching it or drinking it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't go near it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you then sort of spend your time
[SPEAKER_01]: Like dressing it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why do you need to dress it up in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if it's already beautiful and wonderful... Would you dress up a pile of excrement?
[SPEAKER_01]: No amount of dress will make a pile of excrement attractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will only dress up something that you can perceive that can be embellished even more by dressing up, by adorning, by beautifying, by covering up the ugly, so I can emphasize the beautiful, means you imply it's beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already a contradiction in terms, because it isn't beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's beautiful, it would be in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't age.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be subjected to elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be subjected to dying, sickness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be subjected to, basically, everything else that's going on in the body that you conveniently ignore every single time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choose to only single out one aspect that's not as ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_01]: People think things are beautiful and then ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they can say, oh, this is beautiful and less beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, if you practice correctly, sense restraint and develop wisdom, it's gonna be ugly and even more ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing beautiful anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no beauty in danger and peril and deadly suffering and trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's a perfectly engineered, beautifully dressed trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a perilous trap and you are a subject of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will be scared.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not be beautifying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be highlighting its danger, its ugliness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way you would engage in any form of even that tiny bit of beautification is by not seeing the danger and the ugliness of it, by ignoring it, by choosing to not attend to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe, again, it's a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a cover-up, again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of karma action,
[SPEAKER_00]: And the result of action...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is... the result of action, the result of your actions, is reality reasserting itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which reality?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean by reality?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's how nature thinks.
[SPEAKER_01]: What reasserts itself is already that attitude of ignoring and covering up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the proliferation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you engage, the more of the unwholesome karma you do,
[SPEAKER_01]: The result, the direct result, here and now, will be reinforcing of the underlying ignoring of those values, which is what your value is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically underlying wrong views, underlying lack of context of danger, peril, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're reinforcing, that's what grows.
[SPEAKER_00]: It reinforces because it's going against that which is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but that doesn't mean that there which is, it's brought up more.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's simply covered up even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, but... That's why karma keeps you bound to the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that the truth will reveal itself by the more you try to conceal it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the more that you try to conceal it, the more you will try to conceal it, because... Yeah, the more bound to concealment of the truth you become, the more dependent on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It sort of emphasizes...
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: The truth that you... No, you wouldn't use the word truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lie for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It emphasizes your lie.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to lie, there has to be an implicit truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not emphasized.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is emphasized is the lie.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Puthujana has no relationship with the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment he gets it, he becomes a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that he knows the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why it's not correct to say, oh, reinforces or emphasizes the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: For whom?
[SPEAKER_01]: For Sotāpanna, that's not the case, because he got the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: For Puthujana, all thing that's emphasized is a lie.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the statement is abstractly true, what you say, but practically unapplicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why I... that's why I'm saying it's not correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what you're describing in theory, and yes, but that theory, if it's not applicable to either type of individual, it's not a right theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, in order to maintain a lie, you kind of carry the truth with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean you're a step closer to understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if I do something good, I give... there is a result.
[SPEAKER_00]: That emphasizes that which I've just done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I might feel joy...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's non-specific.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might feel joy, I might... you might say thank you, because that act that I've done is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... there's a good result.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of... there's non... By the way, why is generosity good?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is generosity free from discrepancy?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still an action, it's still a kamma, but in itself, why is generosity good?
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no concealment there, there's no cover-up, there's no taking away, which is not... No, I'm still very conceited and arrogant and I gave it to you for selfish reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the act of giving is still good.
[SPEAKER_01]: My reason is really selfish.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't even like you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yet, that act of giving is still good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because that's the degree of this... nothing's been concealed there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where?
[SPEAKER_00]: In that whole act.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm doing it for myself, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm doing it for you, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not pretending that... Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doing things for yourself is concealment through your own conceit, which already misperceives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean... No, no, I'm just talking about the action of giving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the action of taking from you is bad in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The action of giving is good in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is action of giving good in itself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, I mean, before you were saying that, because it emulates that right order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, pretty much, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I would say differently, in a sense that, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving or taking away, as we... well, as we described in the relation to taking things away, fundamentally, you are in no position to exercise any ownership, even on account of your own sense organs, let alone everything else you can experience through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, giving up means relinquishing of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: However symbolic, by the way, you don't even need to think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving something, it mirrors the non-ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mirrors the impossibility to own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mirrors the possibility of relinquishing the ownership, even if you don't make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good karma will not free you from karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can give all you want, but underneath all of that, you still value the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still imply the ownership of your sense of self, your body, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because it emulates that...
[SPEAKER_01]: It emulates that which you don't see nor understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's... that's why... That's why it's good, and that's why it will make you, like, as Guru would say, you'll be reborn in better realms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, that the reserve for those who have not been so dependent in this life on desire, aversion, and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's more in line with the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more in line with the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, you can say...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more in line with the universal principles.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, if I act opposed to those universal principles, I do something unwholesome, I don't know how to say it, is... the result of that
[SPEAKER_01]: The result of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the result of that emphasizes that something is not right.
[SPEAKER_00]: For whom?
[SPEAKER_01]: For a third-person observer?
[SPEAKER_00]: For me.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, you won't see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: More sensuality will bring more sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: More sensuality cannot emphasize the problem of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only you turning away from sensuality, like with your own reflection upon the sensuality you engaged.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're thinking about it accurately, but abstractly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I'm looking at...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I'm looking at another person, I'm looking at you acting badly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I see you get bad results.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I can say I know why you're getting bad results.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not, you know, living in accordance with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going against the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but that...
[SPEAKER_01]: But that means you understand the law of kamma and how I got the bad results on account of this, or...?
[SPEAKER_00]: But can't you understand the law of kamma on that basic... No, you can understand the wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can know whatever goes through the gateway of contradicting that, maintaining that existential contradiction, will be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever goes through the gateway of... And will result in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But to what extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not saying... You don't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aversion and distraction will always result in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot, as the Buddha said, wholesome action cannot have unwholesome results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome action cannot have wholesome results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are you trying to say, still?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the universal law, the nature's law, the principles we were talking about, they're either abstractly true or true in case of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what I was saying was that the result of action is the universal principle asserting itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how I started.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reasserting.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, that's not right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it not right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, explain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the wrong order, unless you're a Sotāpanna or higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing you're reasserting is the wrong order of the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because there are results of actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if there was the right order, would there be results of your actions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you're talking about the order of actual physical action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But except for an arahant, who's gone beyond kamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he is uprooted in kamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hasn't gone beyond it for as long as he's alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, things that he's to experience on the level of body and elements, he will still experience in this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there won't be any future lives for him to experience that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's what I mean, like, by saying that you're in line with universal principle, you're obscuring the fact that you can do good and still not be free from kamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do bad, you can do good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both are doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not rooted in the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're rooted in whether you see the Universal Principle or you don't see the Universal Principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Sotāpanna in highest sees the Universal Principle, which is why he has a limited amount of rebirth and eventually he's completely in parinibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not seeing the Universal Principle means you're still going to be equally reborn just in better places, maybe if you were doing good.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, acting out of non-seeing of universal principle, reasserts the not-seeing of universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to stop acting out of not-seeing the universal principle, as in, you need to stop doing unwholesome things, you need to start being virtuous and keeping the precepts, and then you might get to see the universal principle, because at least you're not contradicting it anymore, on all layers of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not a guarantee you'll still see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be virtuous for the rest of your life and still remain a bhutujjana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing that matters, whether universal principle makes a difference or not, is whether it's seen or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not whether you act with it accordingly or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can act with it accordingly and still not understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's wrong what you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing or not seeing the universal principle is what matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only time a universal principle will be reasserted, is for the one who saw that, which can be now reasserted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, okay, okay, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if... so, you don't see the universal principle, it doesn't mean that it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's a possibility of seeing it is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the universal principle is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a universal principle, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it wouldn't be a universal principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't see it, it doesn't mean that it's not... it's not the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't... What universal principle?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no universal principle, because I don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you're basically perverting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you're bound by it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but that's why then I would be affected by actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not correct to say that that's why you would be reaffirming the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I don't mean to actually imply that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't mean to imply that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know, I know, I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's how you were phrasing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you reassert the universal principle by acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting out cannot reassert the universal principle, because acting out is already within the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that universal principle, that your action cannot step outside, or affirm or deny, your action is the universal principle, can either be seen, which will then free you from action, or not seen, which keeps you bound with the action, and the direction that that action takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeps you bound with the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think, if you want to understand why your statement was wrong to begin with,
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop implying that your action is kind of a response to universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Action is fully enclosed within the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, I'm... Good action, bad action, neutral action, within the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you wouldn't say that that which is already within the universal principle is reaffirming the universal principle by acting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reaffirmation of your action is, again, within the same universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether that principle is understood or not, that's where the issue is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Sotāpanna is one who knows good kamma as good kamma and bad kamma as bad kamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, he doesn't know the results of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he understands that this action is within the right direction of the universal principle, and that he understands that this direction is within the wrong... sorry, this action is within the wrong direction within the universal principle, which is why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the pratyujana acts, but doesn't know the universal principle, which is... That's why he's not free from karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he doesn't know that he's acting...
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can take on faith, on trust, on authority, the reasons for acting good, but that doesn't mean he understood the nature of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he... but he's affected by his actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, his actions will take him in the direction that basically you choose them to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he knows the universal principle?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then that... how far you will go in that direction will be limited.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won't be affected or not... At most in this life, if he's an arahant, and then he'll... he will not be affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like Angulimala.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he went to Pindapad, later on, when he became an arahant, and some people recognized him, and they threw stones and sticks at him, and beating him, and he came back bloodied, bruised, like in pain, and the Buddha said, ah, bear it, Brahmin, bear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are bearing out results of your actions now, which you would have done otherwise for eons to come.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this is it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is all you're gonna have left over from the horrible things you've done is these few stones.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they are... those are the results of his previous actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although he's an arahant, you realize these results are on the level of elements, other people, everything else, basically, that can befall this body, these five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he has a limit because he's out by being an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when this breaks apart, these aggregates, they will be not new ones being taken up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the amount of that direction that can be suffered, endured or enjoyed on account of your good previous actions is sort of cut off, finished.
[SPEAKER_01]: For Sotāpanna, as we say, seven lifetimes, anāgāmī once returned.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it was a measure of your progress and how far you can sort of carry on as a result of previous actions, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for the Sotāpanna, for whatever he does,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be within that span, at most, or even less.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever he does... Let me try again that same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever he does, reasserts the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, it reminds him of that universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because he has understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't say... That's what I mean, like, if you speak in a third-person sense, you can say universal principle is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I said, element of nibbāna is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can... Everybody can, theoretically, develop nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that the one, like, from the point of view of a person, if you're not seeing it, you're not having it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a Sotāpanna has... Sotāpanna seeing it, he has it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, everything would be reaffirming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if he does unwholesome, he will be reminded of the wholesome underlying framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he can't go that far.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he can't go that far in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't go that far in all the actions you can do on account of breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why he can't go that far in on account of the rebirths that will wait for you on account of those bad actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't go that far in
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, like, we can say the statement you said, everything you do reaffirms or reasserts the universal principle is true for Sotāpanna or higher, not for the one below.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you allow puthujjana to partake in that statement, that would equal, like, when people read, oh, the element of nibbāna is present in everyone's experience,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then people assume, ah, we're already in nibbāna, as you have the Mahāyāna schools, saying the Buddha nature and nibbāna is always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like greed, aversion, delusion are symptoms of non-Buddha nature and non-nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom from greed, aversion, delusion means, yes, you can get your Buddha nature and your nibbāna, but you can't have it both.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which one is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: But if people develop a view that this abstract possibility of nibbāna is what nibbāna is, they will not get free from the symptoms that prevent them to get nibbāna here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the Buddha talked about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when a man not free from greed, aversion, delusion, says, oh, I perceive nibbāna, I am in nibbāna, I'm attaining nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, yeah, sometimes, if he made the effort, he would be factually stating that which nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he wouldn't be attaining it, because he's not free from his own conceit
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's not the nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's not the universal principle, because you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just abstractly not applicable to your experience that contradicts it through greed, aversion and dullness and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, theoretically, you are within the universal principle, either, but you're going against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not being free from greed, aversion, delusion, means your values are against the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you act out of the values that are against it, the more you're reinforcing the againstness of values, not that which you're against.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to end or recap, I was saying, what is common to everything that's unwholesome, is that
[SPEAKER_00]: That view of... or that act of misappropriating things, taking that which is not yours, concealing that which is... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what's in common, by the way, to misappropriating, concealing, taking up?
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the common thread?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mūḍhapareyāya 1.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the root of all things.
[SPEAKER_01]: All things are rooted in conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, the fact that you're conceiving already means misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already means putting yourself first, that second, taking the own, implying the ownership, lack of... All of that comes from simple conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am in this, I am from this, this is for me, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is for me, therefore I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, all that, all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was trying to come up with a term for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: A patujana, in that sense, is one who conceives, is a thief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, like, that wouldn't be... it's kind of more like a... it would be an impassionate statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's a thief.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not accurate, because in order to be a thief, you need to perceive the lack of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tujana doesn't perceive that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's a victim of his own ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That results in him being... acting like a thief, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that's not... that conceiving and ignoring these things... it's not on the level of lying to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order to lie to yourself, you know the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just trying to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just ignoring and choosing to always emphasize a certain direction of least resistance, of pleasure, avoidance of pain, all the values that a mind of Bhutujana would be acting out of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality, ill-will and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can now equally choose to not act to, which will then start to reveal that which you have been ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your attention is already implying ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't want to ignore the context, you want to ignore centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: By all means, by the way, engage in avijja towards centrality, towards ill-will and towards delusion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kill avijja, kill the passion, kill ill-will, kill the distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do away with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there are things you should kill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just keep choosing to ignore other things because you keep choosing to follow pleasure and avoid pain, at face value.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start making the effort on account of Buddha's instruction, no, don't attend to this, don't attend to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignore possibility of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to do, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you ignore everything else when you choose to go down the path of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just ignore sensuality and go everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is essential desire, ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't welcome it, don't entertain it, don't engage with it, don't feed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let it die away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reassert the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by ignoring the desire, now you automatically have to look the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way you've been ignoring, by giving in to the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why attention is not, as Buddha said, is not a single thing in the world that will bring sensuality to increase and non-sensuality to decrease as improper attention, as wrong intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is not a single thing in the world that will bring sensuality to decrease and non-sensuality to increase as proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there is a prospect of sensual desire present itself,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take it at a face value and start attending to its beautiful aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would be entertaining you even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, implicitly, you're ignoring the context of peril of it, danger, lack of satisfaction, poison, basically, the threat, the trap, everything in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-beautiful, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you can choose to make the effort to restrain yourself from going down the path of sensuality offered.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, start to reflect on the greater picture, and then, automatically, you cannot be aware of the greater picture of sensuality, which is, oh, this is not really that satisfactory, and at the same time, be equally attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start making effort in the direction of greater picture, you will be less and less pulled by the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your attention determines the direction where your mind will be proliferating to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you attend to centrality, the more you're leaning towards it, the more you will attend to it, the more you lean towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why some people are more dependent on central distraction, some people less.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you have that bigger picture, there's... You have to start cultivating the bigger picture by not taking the little picture at face value and just jumping down it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So sensory strain needs to come first, virtue needs to come first, and then you get to, oh, there is a bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if now I start making even more effort on account of the bigger picture towards the bigger picture and attend that at the expense of attending to the particular picture within it, you'll start withdrawing from centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no matter how far you've proliferated... No matter how far you've proliferated, the way is always up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can go out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how far your preferences went before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that thing can... yeah, it's a dispassion towards that, when you see this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's a dispassion towards whole domain, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you said, that tree, a dead tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a palm stump.
[SPEAKER_01]: Palm stump cut off at the root.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kill the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these branches of... they proliferated in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you were feeding it, they stayed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now it's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: The life of it is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's... that was... that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to be now cutting the branches down.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not going to grow.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot induce more sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all finished.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why an arahant would still remember things he used to enjoy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I used to like this, I used to not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I used to have wives, do like whatever, detain me with the music at night and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I have no desire towards that anymore, but I still remember what I used to enjoy while I was ignorant.